<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Real World Data Science</title>
<link>https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<image>
<url>https://realworlddatascience.net/rss-white-logo.png</url>
<title>Real World Data Science</title>
<link>https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/index.html</link>
<height>58</height>
<width>144</width>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.2.269</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Why large language models should come with a content warning</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian Tarran</dc:creator>
  <link>https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-11-23-LLMs-content-warning/LLM-content-warning.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Anyone who has ever been set a writing task will probably have wished at some point that somebody else could write it for them. As a journalist of 20-plus years, the thought has certainly crossed my mind more than a few times. Which probably explains why a recent headline in Nature caught my attention: <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-03479-w">“Could AI help you to write your next paper?”</a></p>
<p>The article, by Matthew Hutson, looks at how researchers are using artificial intelligence (AI) tools built on large language models (LLMs) as “assistants”. Starting with a prompt, such as “Write a headline for a blog post about large language models being used by academic researchers as research assistants”, an LLM will produce a text output. For example, using the same prompt with <a href="https://openai.com/api/">OpenAI’s GPT-3</a>, I got:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“New research assistants: large language models”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Asked to “Write a headline for a blog post that critiques academic researchers’ use of large language models as research assistants”, GPT-3 produced:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Too much reliance on large language models can hinder research”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And when I asked “Why can too much reliance on large language models hinder research?”, GPT-3 wrote:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“If academic researchers rely too heavily on large language models as research assistants, they may become reliant on the models and may not be able to conduct research without them. This can hinder research because the researchers may not be able to think for themselves and may not be able to come up with new ideas.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A fair point, I suppose. But I sense there’s more to this story, and rather than continue quizzing GPT-3, I sat down with Detlef Nauck, a member of the <a href="../../../../news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/meet-the-team.html">Real World Data Science Editorial Board</a> and head of AI and data science research for BT’s Applied Research Division, to ask a few more questions.</p>
<section id="qa" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="qa">Q&amp;A</h2>
<dl>
<dt>Thanks for joining me today, Detlef. To start, could you give a brief overview of these large language models, what they are, and how they work?</dt>
<dd>
<strong>Detlef Nauck (DN):</strong> Essentially, LLMs match sequences to sequences. Language is treated as a sequence of patterns, and this is based on word context similarity. The way these things work is that they either reuse or create a word vector space, where a word is mapped to something like a 300-dimensional vector based on the context it’s normally found in. In these vector spaces, words like “king” and “queen”, for example, would be very similar to each other, because they appear in similar contexts in the written texts that are used to train these models. Based on this, LLMs can produce coherent sequences of words.
</dd>
</dl>
<p>But the drawback of this approach is that these models have bias, because they are trained with biased language. If you talk about “women”, for example, and you look at which job roles are similar to “women” in a vector space, you find the stereotypically “female” professions but not technical professions, and that is a problem. Let’s say you take the word vector for “man” and the word vector for “king”, and you subtract “man” and then add this to “woman”, then you end up with “queen”. But if you do the same with “man”, “computer scientist”, and “woman”, then you end up maybe at “nurse” or “human resources manager” or something. These models embed the typical bias in society that is expressed through language.</p>
<p>The other issue is that LLMs are massive. GPT-3 has something like 75 billion parameters, and it cost millions to train it from scratch. It’s not energy efficient at all. It’s not sustainable. It’s not something that normal companies can afford. You might need something like a couple of hundred GPUs [graphics processing units] running for a month or so to train an LLM, and this is going to cost millions in cloud environments if you don’t own the hardware yourself. Large tech companies do own the hardware, so for them it’s not a problem. But the carbon that you burn by doing this, you could probably fly around the globe once. So it’s not a sustainable approach to building models.</p>
<p>Also, LLMs are quite expensive to use. If you wanted to use one of these large language models in a contact centre, for example, then you would have to run maybe a few hundred of them in parallel because you get that many requests from customers. But to provide this capacity, the amount of memory needed would be massive, so it is probably still cheaper to use humans – with the added benefit that humans actually understand questions and know what they are talking about.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-11-23-LLMs-content-warning/images/TeresaBerndtsson-LetterWord-Text-Taxonomy-1000x1333.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A black keyboard at the bottom of the picture has an open book on it, with red words in labels floating on top, with a letter A balanced on top of them. The perspective makes the composition form a kind of triangle from the keyboard to the capital A. The AI filter makes it look like a messy, with a kind of cartoon style." width="500"></p>
</figure>
</div>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p>Letter Word Text Taxonomy by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/teresa-berndtsson/">Teresa Berndtsson</a> / <a href="https://www.betterimagesofai.org">Better Images of AI</a> / <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC-BY 4.0</a></p>
</div></div><dl>
<dt>Researchers are obviously quite interested in LLMs, though, and they are asking scientific questions of these models to see what kinds of answers they get.</dt>
<dd>
<strong>DN:</strong> Yes, they are. But you don’t really know what is going to come out of an LLM when you prompt it. And you may need to craft the input to get something out that is useful. Also, LLMs sometimes make up stuff – what the Nature article refers to as “hallucinations”.
</dd>
</dl>
<p>These tools have copyright issues, too. For example, they can generate computer code because code has been part of their training input, but various people have looked into it and found that <a href="https://analyticsindiamag.com/github-copilot-the-latest-in-the-list-of-ai-generative-models-facing-copyright-allegations/">some models generate code verbatim</a> from what others have posted to GitHub. So, it’s not guaranteed that what you get out is actually new text. It might be just regurgitated text. A student might find themselves in a pickle where they think that they have created a text that seems new, but actually it has plagiarism in some of the passages.</p>
<p>There’s an article in <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2020/08/22/1007539/gpt3-openai-language-generator-artificial-intelligence-ai-opinion/">Technology Review</a> that gives some examples of how these systems might fail. People believe these things know what they’re talking about, but they don’t. For them, it’s just pattern recognition. They don’t have actual knowledge representation; they don’t have any concepts embedded.</p>
<dl>
<dt>To summarise, then: LLMs are expensive. They sometimes produce nonsense outputs. And there’s a risk that you’ll be accused of plagiarism if you use the text that’s produced. So, what should our response be to stories like this recent Nature article? How should we calibrate our excitement for LLMs?</dt>
<dd>
<strong>DN:</strong> You have to treat them as a tool, and you have to make sure that you check what they produce. Some people believe if you just make LLMs big enough, we’ll be able to achieve artificial general intelligence. But I don’t believe that, and other people like Geoffrey Hinton and Yann LeCun, they say there’s no way that you get artificial general intelligence through these models, that it’s not going to happen. I’m of the same opinion. These models will be forever limited by the pattern recognition approach that they use.
</dd>
<dt>But, still, is this a technology that you have an eye on in your professional capacity? Are you thinking about how these might be useful somewhere down the line?</dt>
<dd>
<strong>DN:</strong> Absolutely, but we are mainly interested in smaller, more energy efficient, more computationally efficient models that are built on curated language, that can actually hold a conversation, and where you can represent concepts and topics and context explicitly. At the moment, LLMs can only pick up on context by accident – if it is sufficiently expressed in the language that they process – but they might lose track of it if things go on for too long. Essentially, they have a short-term memory: if you prompt them with some text, and they generate text, this stays in their short term memory. But if you prompt them with a long, convoluted sentence, they might not have the capacity to remember what was said at the beginning of the sentence, and so then they lose track of the context. And this is because they don’t explicitly represent context and concepts.
</dd>
</dl>
<p>The other thing is, if you use these systems for dialogues, then you have to script the dialogue. They don’t sustain a dialogue by themselves. You create a dialogue tree, and what they do is they parse the text that comes from the user and then generate a response to it. And the response is then guided by the dialogue tree. But this is quite brittle; it can break. If you run out of dialogue tree, you need to pass the conversation over to a person. Systems like Siri and Alexa are like that, right? They break very quickly. So, you want these systems to be able to sustain conversations based on the correct context.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div quarto-reuse="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</a></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Machine learning</category>
  <category>Large language models</category>
  <category>AI</category>
  <guid>https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-11-23-LLMs-content-warning/LLM-content-warning.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-11-23-LLMs-content-warning/images/TeresaBerndtsson-LetterWord-Text-Taxonomy-1000x1333.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Meet the team</title>
  <dc:creator>Editorial Board</dc:creator>
  <link>https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/meet-the-team.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="editor" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="editor">Editor</h2>
<p><strong>Brian Tarran</strong></p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/Brian.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>I am a writer and editor with 20 years of experience covering the research and data space. I have worked for the Royal Statistical Society (RSS) for the past 8 years, and was editor of <a href="https://www.significancemagazine.com/">Significance Magazine</a> (a joint publication of the RSS, the American Statistical Association and the Statistical Society of Australia) prior to the launch of Real World Data Science. I am a former editor of Research-Live.com and was launch editor of Impact magazine, both published by the Market Research Society.</p>
</section>
<section id="editorial-board" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="editorial-board">Editorial Board</h2>
<p><strong>Sophie Carr (chair)</strong></p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/Sophie.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>I am the founder and owner of Bays Consulting. I trained as an engineer and took a PhD in Bayesian belief networks, and have worked in data analytics ever since. Or to put it another way, I have made a living out of finding patterns. I am the vice-president for education and statistical literacy at the RSS, officially one of the <a href="https://ima.org.uk/12382/worlds-most-interesting-mathematician-2019-dr-sophie-carr/">World’s Most Interesting Mathematicians</a> and was a member of the first cohort of data scientists to achieve the new, defined standard of professionalism award from the <a href="https://alliancefordatascienceprofessionals.com/">Alliance for Data Science Professionals</a>.</p>
<p>I am delighted to be chairing the editorial board of the new data science project from the RSS and am excited to be a part of this project as it evolves into a key resource for all data science practitioners and leaders. To make this a place that helps everyone learn and develop within this field, I’d like to encourage all practitioners, no matter what stage of their career, to submit the type of resource they learn best from (whether that be an article, some code, a data set, a case study or a problem/exercise to solve) on a topic that is important to them – from ethics to analysis plans through to tips on how code. Whatever it is you’re working on that you care about, I’d like to ask you to become an active part of the wonderful community of data scientists by sharing your knowledge.</p>
<p><strong>Sayma Chowdhury</strong></p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/Sayma.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>I am a freelance data scientist on Upwork, with a client portfolio ranging from start-ups to commercial businesses such as supermarkets, pharmaceuticals and automotive manufacturers. I transitioned into data science from law in 2017, having completed a MicroMasters in statistics and data science with MIT and a Professional Certificate in data science with Harvard University. In advance of a PhD in digital humanities, I am currently completing a MicroMasters in data, economy and development policy with MIT and an MSc in data science with the University of Aberdeen. My research interests are in text analytics, natural language processing and machine learning.</p>
<p>The RSS was instrumental in my training and professional development as a data scientist in the early stages of my career, particularly in mastering statistics and R. Data science is a rapidly growing field with employment opportunities in many sectors but there is an increasing need to uphold a realistic and accurate expectation of competency within the industry. I will endeavour to present expert practical guidelines for data scientists as well as demonstrate the versatility of the profession. I hope the site will be a benchmark for academic and professional resources by expert data scientists from industry, accessible to data scientists at all levels, anywhere in the world.</p>
<p><strong>Lee Clewley</strong></p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/Lee.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>I am head of applied AI in GSK’s AI and Machine Learning Group, R&amp;D. I began my career as an astrophysicist, initially working out the mass of our galaxy, before pondering the bigger universe. After six years at Oxford as a post-doc lecturer publishing in theoretical cosmology, I entered the very real world of manufacturing at GSK. For the first five years I applied statistical modelling techniques across manufacturing, such as the first end-to-end continuous manufacturing prototype for tablets. The past decade has been spent as a lead data scientist delivering high value projects across R&amp;D and manufacturing.</p>
<p>I joined this editorial board because the impulse to assemble and present complex data science ideas to a wide range of folks has never left me. I have been a data scientist leader since it became a distinct profession but also have a decent understanding of classical and modern predictive analytics tools and statistics. I have spent a good deal of my adult life teaching students and non-technical adults alike.</p>
<p>I am passionate about delivering useful, pragmatic data science ideas and products to a wide range of people. I enjoy trying to communicate complex scientific information simply. Alongside my peers in the team, I want to support and develop data scientists at whatever stage in their career. I want to help cut through the hype and nonsense to give the best advice possible in a highly respected institution like the RSS.</p>
<p><strong>Jonathan Gillard</strong></p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/Jon.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>I am a professor at the School of Mathematics, Cardiff University, where I am also research group lead for statistics. I have a history of publications in statistical methods and an interest in the theoretical underpinnings of data science, but I have also worked with industry on applied and practical projects. Recent industrial partners of mine include the Office for National Statistics (ONS) and the National Health Service, on projects such as anomaly detection and understanding heterogeneity. Indeed, I am academic chair for Cardiff University’s strategic partnership with the ONS which serves to spur and catalyse collaboration between both organisations.</p>
<p>I am excited to see what this site can achieve. I’m particularly keen to support articles describing the latest, cutting-edge methodology, as well as contributions from data professionals in industry who can explain how data science has managed to offer insights into important problems. Data science is a broad church and I want to ensure that the full array of work in this area is represented on this site. I think the diversity of the editorial board will help promote this objective.</p>
<p><strong>Juhi Gupta</strong></p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/Juhi.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>I am a lecturer in health data sciences and the deputy programme director of the health data science MSc in the School of Health Sciences, University of Manchester (UoM). I have a background in genetics, pharmacology and bioinformatics, and my doctoral thesis focussed on multi-omics data analysis using machine learning methods for precision medicine. I have worked with scientists, clinical academics and technologists to produce translational research. I am currently investigating adverse health outcomes in people with common diseases using electronic health record data, and I also teach on the health informatics MSc joint programme with UoM and UCL.</p>
<p>I would like to see this platform encourage collaborations and the sharing of ideas and good practice across different disciplines that apply data science skills in their work (or as a hobby). I would like to support budding data scientists to gain useful advice and guidance for upskilling as well as application in real-world situations involving health data and biological data.</p>
<p><strong>Hollie Johnson</strong></p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/Hollie.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>I am a data scientist at the National Innovation Centre for Data (NICD), based in Newcastle upon Tyne. Following my undergraduate degree in mathematics, I worked as a software developer both in industry and as a technical research assistant in academia. I later joined the Centre for Doctoral Training in Cloud Computing for Big Data at Newcastle and obtained a PhD in topological data analysis in 2020. Now at the NICD, I specialise in transferring statistics and machine learning skills into industry, through collaborative data science projects.</p>
<p>I am excited to be a member of the editorial board and look forward to seeing Real World Data Science develop into a valuable source of information for aspiring data scientists and professionals alike. I would particularly encourage submissions that demonstrate the use of data science in SMEs and the non-profit sector, as well as perspectives from those with non-standard backgrounds.</p>
<p><strong>Harvey Lewis</strong></p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/Harvey.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>I am a senior technology leader, with a diverse background spanning rocket science, data science and research. I have 30 years of experience in artificial intelligence and other emerging technologies and am currently pioneering the use of AI in Ernst &amp; Young’s tax and law practice. I’m a former member of the Open Data User Group, the Public Sector Transparency Board and the Advisory Committee to the All-Party Parliamentary Group on AI. I am a member of techUK’s leadership committee for data analytics and AI, and an honorary senior visiting fellow at The Bayes Business School in London.</p>
<p>I’m passionate about data science but I’m also a fierce advocate for human skills, which are as often underrated as AI is over-hyped. As a member of the editorial board, I’m keen to explore the interplay between artificial and human intelligence in businesses. I’m going to encourage all data scientists to think about the fundamentally human aspects of their work, such as trust and safety, so that we maintain perspective and proportionality in the face of ever-more sophisticated technology.</p>
<p><strong>Detlef Nauck</strong></p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/Detlef.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>I am a BT Distinguished Engineer and the head of AI and data science research for BT’s Applied Research Division located at Adastral Park, Ipswich, UK. I have over 30 years of experience in AI and machine learning and lead a programme spanning the work of a large team of international researchers who develop capabilities underpinning future AI systems. A key part of this work is to establish best practices in data science and machine learning, leading to the deployment of responsible and auditable AI solutions that are driving real business value.</p>
<p>I am a computer scientist by training and hold a PhD and a Postdoctoral Degree (Habilitation) in machine learning and data analytics. I am also a visiting professor at Bournemouth University and a private docent at the Otto-von-Guericke University of Magdeburg, Germany. I have published 3 books and over 120 papers, and I hold 15 patents and have 30 active patent applications.</p>
<p>I am passionate about promoting best practice in data science and believe that in the UK the RSS is the ideal professional body to pursue this goal. For me, Real World Data Science is an opportunity to share my experience and inspire a new generation of data scientists.</p>
<p><strong>Fatemeh Torabi</strong></p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/Fatemeh.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>I am a research officer and data scientist at Health Data Research UK and a fellow of the RSS. My background is in mathematical statistics and health data science, and my research interests span novel analytical and computational methods for statistical inference in panel data and population health. I am supporting the development of the Real World Data Science platform in the context of health with a specific focus on how health data can be harnessed through data linkage and analysis to answer important questions and improve the lives of our population.</p>
<p><strong>Isabel Sassoon</strong></p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/Isabel.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>I am a senior lecturer in computer science (data science) at Brunel University and the programme lead for the data science and analytics MSc programme. My research interests are in data-driven automated reasoning and its transparency and explainability, which brings in data science and artificial intelligence with applications within the health space. I am also championing open science and reproducible analysis in both my research and teaching. I have a PhD in informatics from King’s College London and it was on the topic related to the use of AI to support statistical model selection. Prior to Brunel I was a teaching fellow and research associate at King’s College London and before that I worked for more than 10 years as a data science consultant in industry, including 8 years at SAS UK. </p>
<p>I have been working, researching, consulting and teaching in the data science space for a while and I am passionate about the domain and its applications. I am always interested in sharing and hearing what else is being done to support, inform and inspire all those studying and working in the field of data science. I look forward to sharing case studies, how-to guides and data science profiles through this website.</p>
<p><strong>Christopher Thiele</strong></p>

<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/Christopher.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p>I’m a principal data scientist at Uniper where I lead a team that focuses mainly on financial business processes and upskilling initiatives. We run projects end to end: from use case ideation, requirement collection and translation to prototyping, assessment, deployment and maintenance. Besides the core analytical and data engineering duties, overarching topics such as data design, data governance and data strategy predominate my days. In my previous role, at the German Economic Institute, I contributed to the development of a cross-functional department that helps apply data science methods in economic research. Projects often involve geospatial analyses or natural language processing. Before that, I worked as a data scientist in customer and marketing analytics, doing statistical analyses such as marketing mix modelling. I have a master’s degree in statistics from Warwick University, a bachelor’s degree in economics from the University of Cologne and I’m trained as an assistant tax consultant in Germany.</p>
<p>I see data science as a creative way to solve problems using software engineering and quantitative modelling techniques and I like to build software pieces that people can interact with. I think that there still exists a lot of confusion about data science as a discipline. Reducing it would promote the realisation of its potential for individuals, as a profession, and our society, as a form of digitalisation. I hope that with Real World Data Science we can provide guidance and clarification to everybody engaged or interested in the field and accompany this young profession’s development.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>People</category>
  <category>Biographies</category>
  <guid>https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/meet-the-team.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://realworlddatascience.net/news-and-views/editors-blog/posts/2022-10-18-meet-the-team/images/team.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="64" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
